By birth and by choice,
بالولادة وبالاختيار,
I've been involved with the auto industry my entire life,
كنت مولعا بصناعة السيارات في كل جوانب حياتي,
and for the past 30 years,
وطوال ال 30 عاما الماضية,
I've worked at Ford Motor Company.
عملت في شركة فورد للسيارات.
And for most of those years,
وخلال معظم تلك السنوات,
I worried about,
كنت قلقا بخصوص
how am I going to sell more cars and trucks?
كيف يمكنني ان ابيع عدد اكبر من السيارات والشاحنات؟
But today I worry about,
لكنني اليوم قلق بخصوص,
what if all we do is sell more cars and trucks?
ماذا لو كان كل ما نفعله هو بيع المزيد من السيارات والشاحنات؟
What happens
ماذا سيحصل
when the number of vehicles on the road doubles, triples,
عندما تتضاعف اعداد المركبات في الطريق مرتان وثلاثة,
or even quadruples?
او ربما اربعة اضعاف؟
My life is guided by two great passions,
هناك عاطفتان اسهمتا في توجيه حياتي,
and the first is automobiles.
الاولى هي السيارات.
I literally grew up with the Ford Motor Company.
حرفيا لقد نشأت مع شركة فورد لصناعة السيارات.
I thought it was so cool as a little boy
اعتقد انه كان شيئا جميلا بالنسبة لي كيافع
when my dad would bring home the latest Ford or Lincoln
عندما كان والدي يجلب الى المنزل احدث طرازات سيارات فورد او لينكون
and leave it in the driveway.
ويتركها في الطريق.
And I decided about that time, about age 10,
وقررت وكنت في العاشرة من عمري حينها
that it would be really cool if I was a test driver.
انه سوف يكون شيئا جميلا لو اصبحت قائد اختبار المركبات.
So my parents would go to dinner.
عندما يذهب والدي لتناول العشاء.
They'd sit down; I'd sneak out of the house.
كانا يجلسان , وكنت اتسلل خارج المنزل.
I'd jump behind the wheel and take the new model around the driveway,
وكنت اقفز خلف المقود وانطلق بالطراز الجديد في جولة على الطريق,
and it was a blast.
وكان ذلك غاية في الروعه
And that went on for about two years,
واستمر ذلك الحال لمدة عامين تقريبا,
until -- I think I was about 12 --
الى ان وكنت في الثانية عشر من عمري حينها
my dad brought home
احضر والدي الى المنزل
a Lincoln Mark III.
سيارة من طراز لينكون مارك 3
And it was snowing that day.
وكانت تثلج في ذلك اليوم.
So he and mom went to dinner,
وذهب هو ووالدتي الى العشاء
and I snuck out
وتسللت خارجا
and thought it'd be really cool to do donuts
واعتقدت انه سوف يكون ممتعا رسم الدونات
or even some figure-eights in the snow.
او الرقم ثمانيه على الثلج.
My dad finished dinner early that evening.
والدي فرغ من العشاء باكرا في ذلك المساء.
And he was walking to the front hall
وكان يسير الى القاعة الامامية
and out the front door
خارجا من الباب الامامي
just about the same time I hit some ice
في نفس الوقت الذي اصتدمت به بقطع من الثلج الصلب
and met him at the front door with the car --
وقابلته في الباب الامامي بالسيارة
and almost ended up in the front hall.
وانتهينا جميعا في القاعة الامامية.
So it kind of cooled my test-driving for a little while.
وكان ذلك سببا في تجميد قيادتي التجريبية لبعض الوقت.
But I really began to love cars then.
لكنني من حينها بدأت حقيقة احب السيارات
And my first car was a 1975 electric-green Mustang.
واول سيارة امتلكتها كانت موستينج خضرا ء 1975.
And even though the color was pretty hideous,
وبالرغم من ان اللون كان حقا بشع,
I did love the car,
لكنني احببت السيارة,
and it really cemented my love affair with cars
وبالفعل رسخت مسألة حبي للسيارات
that's continued on to this day.
بحيث استمرت الى يومنا هذا.
But cars are really more than a passion of mine;
لكن السيارات كانت تمثل لي شيئ يفوق العشق,
they're quite literally in my blood.
حرفيا هو شيئ يجري في دمي
My great grandfather was Henry Ford,
جدي الاول هو هينري فورد,
and on my mother's side,
ومن جهة والدتي
my great grandfather was Harvey Firestone.
جدي الاول هو هارفي فايرستون صاحب مصانع الاطارات.
So when I was born,
ولذلك عندما ولدت,
I guess you could say expectations were kind of high for me.
التوقعات كانت نوعا ما عالية بالنسبة لي.
But my great grandfather, Henry Ford,
لكن جدي الاول هنري فورد,
really believed that the mission of the Ford Motor Company
كان يؤمن حقيقة ان مهمة شركة فورد لصناعة السيارات
was to make people's lives better
هي ان تجعل الناس تعيش بصورة افضل
and make cars affordable so that everyone could have them.
وجعل السيارات في متناول اليد بحيث يستطيع كل شخص ان يحصل عليها.
Because he believed that with mobility
لانه كان يؤمن ان قابلية التنقفل
comes freedom and progress.
يجلب الحرية والانجاز.
And that's a belief that I share.
وهذا الايمان الذي اتشارك فيه معه.
My other great passion is the environment.
عشقي الاخر هو البيئه.
And as a young boy, I used to go up to Northern Michigan
وكشاب يافع كنت اذهب عادة الى شمال ميتشاجين
and fish in the rivers that Hemingway fished in
وكنت اصطاد في نفس الانهر التي كان يصطاد فيها المؤلف هيمينجواي
and then later wrote about.
والتي كتب عنها لاحقا
And it really struck me
ولقد صدمني
as the years went by,
انه بمضي السنين
in a very negative way,
وبصورة سلبية للغاية
when I would go to some stream that I'd loved,
عندما ذهبت الى بعض الجداول التي احببتها,
and was used to walking through this field
وكنت معتادا ان امشي بجوارها خلال الحقول,
that was once filled with fireflies,
والتي كانت مليئة باليراعات
and now had a strip mall or a bunch of condos on it.
والتي حل محلها المراكز التجارية او الشقق السكنية.
And so even at a young age,
وايضا وبالرغم من السن المبكرة,
that really resonated with me,
كان لذلك صدى كبير في داخلي
and the whole notion of environmental preservation,
و فكرة الحماية البيئية كاملة,
at a very basic level, sunk in with me.
وبصورة اساسية غاصت في أعماقي.
As a high-schooler, I started to read
عندما كنت في المراحل الدراسية المتقدمة بدأت القراءة
authors like Thoreau and Aldo Leopold
لمؤلفين مثل ثوريو والدو ليوبولد
and Edward Abbey,
و ايدوارد ابي.
and I really began to develop
وبدأت فعليا في تكوين
a deeper appreciation of the natural world.
تقدير عميق لعالم الطبيعة.
But it never really occurred to me
ولم يدر بخلدي
that my love of cars and trucks
ان عشقي للسيارات والشاحنات
would ever be in conflict with nature.
سوف يصطدم بعشي للطبيعة.
And that was true
وكان ذلك حقيقة
until I got to college.
حتى التحقت بالجامعة
And when I got to college, you can imagine my surprise
ولك ان تتخيل مفاجأتي عند التحاقي بالجامعة
when I would go to class
عندما اذهب الى الفصل الدراسي
and a number of my professors would say
وكان عدد من البروفيسورات يقولون
that Ford Motor Company and my family
ان شركة فورد للسيارات وعائلتي
was everything that was wrong with our country.
فعلو كل شيئ سيء للبلاد.
They thought that we were more interested, as an industry,
كانو يعتقدون اننا كنا مهتمين كأرباب صناعة,
in profits, rather than progress,
بالربح المالي اكثر من التقدم
and that we filled the skies with smog --
واننا ملأنا السماء بالدخان الاسود
and frankly, we were the enemy.
وبشكل صريح نحن اعداء الوطن.
I joined Ford after college,
التحقت بشركة فورد بعد التخرج,
after some soul searching
وبعد بحث روحي
whether or not this is really the right thing to do.
فيما اذا كان ذلك هو الشيء الصحيح الذي يمكن فعله.
But I decided that I wanted to go
قررت الذهاب الى الشركة
and see if I could affect change there.
والنظر فيما اذا كنت سأحدث اي تغيير هناك.
And as I look back over 30 years ago,
وعندما انظر الى الوراء 30 عاما مضت,
it was a little naive to think at that age
كان ذلك نوعا من السذاجة التفكير في تلك السن
that I could. But I wanted to.
انني استطيع ,لكنني اردت ذلك.
And I really discovered
وحقيقة اكتشفت
that my professors weren't completely wrong.
انا اساتذتي لم يكونو مخطئين تماما.
In fact, when I got back to Detroit,
في الواقع, عندما عدت الى ديترويت,
my environmental leanings weren't exactly embraced
لم تكن ميولي البيئية مُعتنقة
by those in my own company,
من قبل اولئك الاشخاص في شركتنا,
and certainly by those in the industry.
وكذلك من قبل الاخرين في القطاع الصناعي.
I had some very interesting conversations,
كانت لدي احاديث ممتعة
as you can imagine.
كما يمكنكم التخيل
There were some within Ford
هناك مع بعض الاشخاص داخل فورد
who believed that all this ecological nonsense
والذين كان يعتقدون ان ذلك الهراء حول البيئة
should just disappear
يجب ان يختفي
and that I needed to stop hanging out
وانه يتوجب علي الكف عن مصاحبة
with "environmental wackos."
"مجانين البيئة"
I was considered a radical.
كنت اعتبر شخص متطرف.
And I'll never forget the day I was called in by a member of top management
ولن انسى ابدا ذلك اليوم الذي تم فيه استدعائي من قبل احد كبار المدراء,
and told to stop associating
وطلب فيه من التوقف عن الاقتران
with any known or suspected environmentalists.
بأي من عُرف عنه شبهة الناشط البيئي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Of course, I had no intention of doing that,
بالطبع لم يكن لدي اي نية لعمل ذلك.
and I kept speaking out about the environment,
وواصلت الحديث عن البيئة.
and it really was the topic
وكان ذلك هو الموضوع
that we now today call sustainability.
الذي تمثله الاستدامة في وقتنا الحالي
And in time, my views went from controversial
وبمرور الوقت تحول موقفي من الجدل
to more or less consensus today.
الى الاجماع بصورة او باخرى.
I mean, I think most people in the industry
اعني,اظن ان معظم الاشخاص في الصناعة
understand that we've got to get on with it.
يفهمون انه يجب علينا الخوض في هذا
And the good news is today we are tackling the big issues,
والخبر الجيد اننا اليوم نعالج قضية كبيرة
of cars and the environment --
تخص السيارات والبيئة--
not only at Ford, but really as an industry.
ليس فقط في شركة فورد ولكن في الصناعة ذاتها
We're pushing fuel efficiency to new heights.
نحاول رفع مستوى كفاءة الوقود أكثر
And with new technology,
وباستخدام التقنية الجديدة,
we're reducing -- and I believe, someday we'll eliminate --
نقوم بتخفيض -- واعتقد في يوم ما سوف نلغيها--
CO2 emissions.
انبعاثات ثاني اكسيد الكربون
We're starting to sell electric cars, which is great.
بدأنا بيع سيارات كهربائية وذلك شيء عظيم.
We're developing alternative powertrains
ونطور بدائل لقطارات الطاقة
that are going to make cars affordable
والتي سوف تجعل السيارات باسعار معقولة
in every sense of the word --
وبكل ما تحويه الكلمة من معنى --
economically, socially
اقتصادي,اجتماعي
and environmentally.
و بيئي
And actually, although we've got a long way to go
وفي الواقع وبالرغم من انه امامنا طريق طويل
and a lot of work to do,
والكثير من العمل
I can see the day where my two great passions --
اعتقد انني سوف ارى اليوم الذي يكون فيه عشقي
cars and the environment --
السيارات والبيئة--
actually come into harmony.
يمضيان في تناغم.
But unfortunately,
ولكن للاسف,
as we're on our way to solving one monstrous problem --
عندما كنا منشغلين بحل مشكلة رهيبة--
and as I said, we're not there yet; we've got a lot of work to do,
وكما قلت لم ننتهي من ذلك وامامنا الكثير من العمل
but I can see where we will --
ولكنني استطيع ان ارى ذلك ممكنا--
but even as we're in the process of doing that,
ولكن بالرغم اننا في عملية انجاز ذلك,
another huge problem is looming,
تفاقمت مشكلة ضخمة اخرى
and people aren't noticing.
والناس غير منتبهين.
And that is the freedom of mobility
وتلك هي حرية الانتقال
that my great grandfather brought to people
التي قدمها جدي الاول الى الناس
is now being threatened, just as the environment is.
يتم تهديدها الان ,تماما مثل البيئة
The problem, put in its simplest terms,
والمشكلة بعبارات سهلة
is one of mathematics.
هي حسابية.
Today there are approximately 6.8 billion people in the world,
اليوم يوجد حوالي 6.8 بليون انسان في العالم
and within our lifetime, that number's going to grow
وخلال فترة وجودنا هذا الرقم سوف يزيد
to about nine billion.
الى حوالي 9 بليون.
And at that population level,
وعند هذا الحد من التعداد السكاني,
our planet will be dealing with the limits of growth.
سوف يتعامل كوكبنا مع محددات للنمو.
And with that growth
وبذلك النمو
comes some severe practical problems,
تظهر بعض المشاكل العملية الحادة
one of which is our transportation system
احدها نظام النقل
simply won't be able to deal with it.
ببساطة لن يمكن التعامل معه
When we look at the population growth in terms of cars,
عندما ننظر لهذا النمو السكاني من زاوية السيارات
it becomes even clearer.
سوف يكون اكثر وضوحا
Today there are about 800 million cars on the road worldwide.
اليوم توجد حوالي ال 800 مليون سيارة على الطرقات في انحاء العالم
But with more people
ولكن مع تزايد الناس
and greater prosperity around the world,
وازدياد الازدهار حول العالم
that number's going to grow
ذلك الرقم سوف يزيد
to between two and four billion cars by mid century.
لحوالي ثنان واربعة بليون سيارة في منتصف القرن.
And this is going to create the kind of global gridlock
وذلك سوف يوصلنا الى اختناق مروري عالمي
that the world has never seen before.
لم يرى مثله العالم من قبل.
Now think about the impact
الان فكرو في التاثير
that this is going to have on our daily lives.
الذي سوف يطرأ على حياتنا اليومية
Today the average American
اليوم المتوسط الامريكي
spends about a week a year
هو حوالي اسبوع من كل عام
stuck in traffic jams,
يضيع في الاختناقات المرورية
and that's a huge waste of time and resources.
وذلك اهدار عظيم للوقت والموارد
But that's nothing compared
لكن ذلك لا شيئ بالمقارنة
to what's going on
بما سوف يحدث مستقبلا
in the nations that are growing the fastest.
في الامم التي تنمو سريعا
Today the average driver in Beijing
اليوم متوسط القيادة في العاصمة الصينية بكين
has a five-hour commute.
حوالي خمسة ساعات
And last summer -- many of you probably saw this --
وفي الصيف الماضي-- الكثير منكم لربما شاهدو هذا--
there was a hundred-mile traffic jam
كان هناك مئات الاميال من الازدحام المروري
that took 11 days to clear in China.
استغرق انهائها 11 يوما في الصين.
In the decades to come,
في العقد القادم
75 percent of the world's population
75 في المئة من السكان في العالم
will live in cities,
سوف يعيشون في المدن,
and 50 of those cities
و 50 في المئة من تلك المدن
will be of 10 million people or more.
سوف يقطنها 10 مليون شخص وأكثر
So you can see the size of the issue that we're facing.
لذا يمكنكم رؤية حجم المشكلة التي سوف نواجهها
When you factor in population growth,
عندما تحلل النمو السكاني
it's clear that the mobility model that we have today
يكون من الواضح ان نموذج النقل الذي نطبقه اليوم
simply will not work tomorrow.
ببساطه لن يعد مجديا في الغد.
Frankly, four billion clean cars on the road
بأمانة,4 ملايين سيارة نظيفة في الطريق
are still four billion cars,
لا تزال اربعة مليون سيارة
and a traffic jam with no emissions
والاختناق المروري بدون انبعاثات
is still a traffic jam.
يظل اختناقا مروريا
So, if we make no changes today,
لذلك ان لم نقم بالتغييرات اليوم
what does tomorrow look like?
مالذي سوف يبدو عليه الغد؟
Well I think you probably already have the picture.
اعتقد انها ربما لديكم الان صورة لما سيحدث
Traffic jams are just a symptom of this challenge,
الاختناقات المرورية هي علامة واحدة من هذا التحدي
and they're really very, very inconvenient,
وهي غير مريحة جدا جدا
but that's all they are.
لكن هذا واقعها
But the bigger issue
لكن القضية الاكبر
is that global gridlock
ان ذلك الاختناق المروري العالمي
is going to stifle economic growth
سوف يخنق النمو الاقتصادي
and our ability to deliver
وقدرتنا على ارسال
food and health care,
الغذاء والمساعدات الطبية,
particularly to people that live in city centers.
خاصة لاؤلئك الاشخاص الذين يعيشون في وسط المدن
And our quality of life is going to be severely compromised.
ومستوى معيشتنا سوف يكون في خطر شديد
So what's going to solve this?
اذا ماهو الحل لكل هذا؟
Well the answer isn't going to be more of the same.
حسنا الاجابة لن تكون الكثير من نفس الشيء
My great grandfather once said
جدي الاول قال في احد المرات
before he invented the Model T,
قبل ان يخترع سيارته ذات الموديل تي
"If I had asked people then what they wanted,
"لو سألت الناس مالذي يريدونه,
they would have answered,
سوف يجيبون,
'We want faster horses.'"
"نريد احصنة اسرع ""
So the answer to more cars
اذا الاجابة عن السيارات الكثيرة
is simply not to have more roads.
ببساطة لن يكون ايجاد المزيد من الطرق.
When America began moving west,
عندما توجه الامريكيين للغرب
we didn't add more wagon trains,
لم نزف المزيد من العربات المقطورة,
we built railroads.
لقد بنينا سككا حديدية
And to connect our country after World War II,
ولربط دولتنا بعد الحرب العالمية الثانية,
we didn't build more two-lane highways,
لم ننشئ المزيد من الطرق السريعة المزدوجه
we built the interstate highway system.
بنينا نظام خطوط سريعة بين الولايات.
Today we need that same leap in thinking
اليوم يجب ان يكون ذلك التفكير البعيد المدى
for us to create a viable future.
لاجلنا لننشئ مستقبل منظور,
We are going to build smart cars,
سوف نبني سيارات ذكية
but we also need to build
لكن ايضا نحتاج لبناء
smart roads, smart parking,
طرق ذكية ومواقف ذكية,
smart public transportation systems and more.
ونظام مواصلات عامة ذكية والمزيد
We don't want to waste our time
لا نريد اهدار وقتنا
sitting in traffic, sitting at tollbooths
جالسين في الزحام، أو في مقصورات كبيرة
or looking for parking spots.
او البحث عن مكان للوقوف
We need an integrated system
نريد نظاما متكاملا
that uses real time data
يستخدم بيانات لحظية
to optimize personal mobility on a massive scale
ليستغل الانتقال الشخصي افضل استغلال
without hassle or compromises for travelers.
بدون صراعات او تنازلات للمتنقلين
And frankly, that's the kind of system
وبصراحة ذلك النوع من الانظمة
that's going to make the future of personal mobility sustainable.
هو الذي سوف يجعل مستقبل التنقل الشخصي محتملا.
Now the good news is some of this work has already begun
الان الخبر الجيد ان بعضا من ذلك العمل قد بدأ
in different parts of the world.
في اماكن مختلفة من العالم
The city of Masdar in Abu Dhabi
في مدينة مصدر في ابوظبي
uses driverless electric vehicles
يستخدمون مركبات بدون سائقين
that can communicate with one another,
يمكنها التواصل مع بعضها البعض
and they go underneath the city streets.
وتتجول تحت شوارع المدينة
And up above, you've got a series of pedestrian walkways.
وفي الاعلى لديك سلسلة من مسالك المشاة.
On New York City's 34th Street,
في مدينة نيويورك شارع 34
gridlock will soon be replaced
الاختناق المروي سوف يستبدل قريبا
with a connected system
بنظام مترابط
of vehicle-specific corridors.
لممرات محددة للسيارات
Pedestrian zones and dedicated traffic lanes are going to be created,
مناطق للمشاة ومسارات مخصصة للمرور سوف يتم انشاؤها ايضا
and all of this will cut down the average rush hour commute
وكل ذلك سوف يقلل من ساعة الذروة
to get across town in New York
التي يستغرقها الانتقال عبر المدينة في نيويورك
from about an hour today at rush hour
من حوالي الساعة يوميا
to about 20 minutes.
الى حوال 20 دقيقة
Now if you look at Hong Kong,
الان لو نظرت الى هونغ كونغ.
they have a very interesting system called Octopus there.
لديهم نظام مثير للاهتمام يسمونه الاخطبوط
It's a system that really ties together
ذلك النظام يربط معا
all the transportation assets
جميع متعلقات النقل
into a single payment system.
في نظام دفع موحد
So parking garages, buses, trains,
المواقف ,البصات,القطارات,
they all operate within the same system.
جميعها تشغل بواسطة نفس النظام
Now shared car services
الان خدمات السيارات المشتركة
are also springing up around the world,
تظهر حول العالم
and these efforts, I think, are great.
وتلك الجهود تبدو عظيمة
They're relieving congestion,
انهم يخففون الاختناقات,
and they're frankly starting to save some fuel.
وهم بامانة بدأوا يوفرون بعض الوقود.
These are all really good ideas
تلك حقا افكار رائعة
that will move us forward.
سوف تنقلنا للامام
But what really inspires me
لكن ما يلهمني حقا
is what's going to be possible
هو مالذي سيكون ممكنا
when our cars can begin talking to each other.
عندما تتمكن سياراتنا من الحديث لبعضها البعض
Very soon, the same systems that we use today
قريبا جدا,نفس النظام الذي نستخدمه اليوم
to bring music and entertainment
لجلب الموسيقى والترفيه
and GPS information into our vehicles
ومعلومات تحديد المواقع الى مركباتنا
are going to be used to create
سوف يستخدم لانشاء
a smart vehicle network.
شبكة مركبات ذكية
Every morning I drive about 30 miles
في كل يوم اقود لمسافة 30 ميل
from my home in Ann Arbor to my office in Dearborn, Michigan.
من منزلي في ان اربور الى مكتبي في ديربورن ,ميتشغان.
And every night I go home,
وفي كل يوم اعود الى منزلي,
my commute is a total crapshoot.
ساعات التنقل يبدو كنوع من الحماقة
And I often have to leave the freeway
وغالبا اجد نفسي مضطرا لترك الطريق المجاني
and look for different ways
والبحث عن طرق اخرى
for me to try and make it home.
ذلك ما يحصل معي للوصول للمنزل.
But very soon we're going to see the days
لكن قريب سوف نرى الايام
when cars are essentially talking to each other.
التي تتحدث فيها السيارات لبعضها البعض
So if the car ahead of me on I-94 hits traffic,
فمثلا لون السيارة التي امامي اي-94 وقعت في زحام
it will immediately alert my car
سوف تنبه سياراتي فورا
and tell my car to reroute itself
وتطلب منها اعادة توجيه نفسها
to get me home in the best possible way.
لتوصلني الى المنزل عبر افضل طريق.
And these systems are being tested right now,
وتلك الانظمة تم اختبارها الان
and frankly they're going to be ready for prime time pretty soon.
وبأمانة سوف تكون جاهزة للظهور للعلن قريبا جدا.
But the potential of a connected car network
لكن ما يمكن عمله عبر شبكة السيارات المترابطة
is almost limitless.
لا حدود له
So just imagine:
تخيل مثلا:
one day very soon,
في يوم ما قريب,
you're going to be able to plan a trip downtown
سوف يمكنك تخطيط رحلتك الى وسط البلد
and your car will be connected to a smart parking system.
وسيارتك سوف تكون مرتبطة بنظام مواقف ذكي
So you get in your car,
سوف تركب سيارتك
and as you get in your car,
وبمجرد دخولك الى السياره
your car will reserve you a parking spot before you arrive --
سوف تحجز سيارتك موقفا لك قبل وصولك--
no more driving around looking for one,
لامزيد من التجول في المنطقة بحثا عن موقف,
which frankly is one of the biggest users of fuel
والذي هو احد اكبر مصادر استهلاك الوقود
in today's cars in urban areas --
في سيارتنا اليوم في المناطق المزدحمة
is looking for parking spots.
هو البحث عن اماكن للوقوف.
Or think about being in New York City
او فكر في انك موجود في مدينة نيويورك
and tracking down an intelligent cab on your smart phone
وتبحث عن سيارة اجرة ذكية باستخدام هاتفك الذكي
so you don't have to wait in the cold to hail one.
اذا لن يتوجب عليك الانتظار في البرد بحثا عن احداها
Or being at a future TED Conference
او تخيل انك موجود في مؤتمر تيد
and having your car
وانت في سيارتك
talk to the calendars of everybody here
التي تتحدث الى اجندات جميع الحضور هنا
and telling you all the best route to take home
وتخبرك بافضل طريق تسلكه لمنزلك ,
and when you should leave
ومتى يجب عليك المغادرة,
so that you can all arrive at your next destination on time.
وبالتالي تستطيعون جميعا الوصول الى وجهتكم في الوقت المناسب.
This is the kind of technology
هذا النوع من التكنولوجيا
that will merge millions of individual vehicles
سوف يدمج الملايين من المركبات
into a single system.
في نظام واحد
So I think it's clear we have the beginnings of a solution
اذا اعتقد انه من الواضح انه يوجد لدينا بداية حل
to this enormous problem.
لهذه المشكلة الهائلة
But as we found out with addressing CO2 issues,
ولكن كما وجدنا عند مجابهة مشاكل ثاني اكسيد الكربون
and also fossil fuels,
وايضا الوقود العضوي
there is no one silver bullet.
لا يوجد هناك حل سحري
The solution is not going to be
الحل لن يكون
more cars, more roads or a new rail system;
المزيد من السيارات,المزيد من الطرق او نظام سكك جديد
it can only be found, I believe,
الحل سيكون في اعتقادي
in a global network
في شبكة عالمية
of interconnected solutions.
من الحلول المترابطة
Now I know we can develop the technology
اعلم الان انه يمكننا تطوير تقنية
that's going to make this work,
سوف تقوم بهذا العمل
but we've got to be willing to get out there
لكن يجب ان يكون لدينا العزيمة للخروج
and seek out the solutions --
والبحث عن حلول --
whether that means vehicle sharing or public transportation
سواء كان ذلك بمشاركة المركبات او المواصلات العامة
or some other way we haven't even thought of yet;
او طريقة اخرى لم نقم بالتفكير بها حتى الان,
our overall transportation-mix and infrastructure
الخليط العام من البنية التحتية والمواصلات
must support all the future options.
يجب ان يدعم جميع الخيارات المستقبلية.
We need our best and our brightest
نريد افضل ما لدينا وواجهة مشرقة
to start entertaining this issue.
لنبدا بهذا الموضوع المسلي
Companies, entrepreneurs, venture capitalists,
الشركات,رجال الاعمال, رؤوس الاموال
they all need to understand
جميعهم يجب عليها ان يعوا
this is a huge business opportunity,
أن هذه فرصة عمل عظيمة
as well as an enormous social problem.
وفي نفس الوقت مشكلة اجتماعية كبيرة
And just as these groups
وتماما مثلما قامت هذه المجموعات
embrace the green energy challenge --
باحتضان تحدي الطاقة الخضراء --
and it's really been amazing to me to watch
وكان ذلك مذهلا حقا بالنسبة لي ان ارى
how much brain power, how much money
كم من الطاقة العقلية وكم من المال
and how much serious thought
وكم من الافكار الجادة
has, really over the last three years,
تمت في الثلاث سنين الاخيرة,
just poured into the green energy field.
صبت جميعها في مجال الطاقة الخضراء
We need that same kind of passion and energy
نحتاج لنفس هذ النوع من الطاقة والعاطفة
to attack global gridlock.
لمهاجمة الاختناق المروري العالمي
But we need people like all of you in this room,
ولكننا نحتاج اناسا يشبهون جميع من في هذه القاعة,
leading thinkers.
مفكرين قاده
I mean, frankly, I need all of you
اعني انني بامانة اريدكم جميعا
to think about how
ان تفكرو كيف
you can help solve this huge issue.
بامكانكم حل هذه المعضله الضخمة
And we need people from all walks of life;
ونحتاج اناسا من مختلف مناحي الحياة
not just inventors, we need policymakers
ليس فقط المخترعين,نحتاج صناع القرار
and government officials
ومسئولي الحكومة
to also think about how they're going to respond to this challenge.
ان يفكرو ايضا كيف يمكنهم الاستجابة لهذا التحدي.
This isn't going to be solved
هذه المشكلة لن تحل
by any one person or one group.
بواسطة شخص او مجموعة
It's going to really require a national energy policy,
سوف تتطلب سياسة طاقة وطنية
frankly for each country,
وذلك ينطبق على كل دولة
because the solutions in each country are going to be different
لان الحلول في كل دولة سوف تكون مختلفة
based upon income levels, traffic jams
اعتمادا على مستوى الدخل والاختناقات المرورية
and also how integrated
وايضا كيف يتم ربط
the systems already are.
الانظمة الموجودة حاليا هناك
But we need to get going, and we need to get going today.
لكننا يجب ان نمضي قدما وان نفعل ذلك اليوم
And we must have an infrastructure
ويجب علينا ان يكون لدينا بنية تحتية
that's designed to support
تكون صممت لدعم
this flexible future.
هذا المستقبل المرن
You know, we've come a long way.
كما تعلمون بدأنا
Since the Model T,
منذ صناعة السيارة "تي"
most people never traveled
لم يكن معظم الناس قد تنقل
more than 25 miles from home in their entire lifetime.
في حياته لمسافة تتجاوز ال 25 ميلا بعيدا من المنزل
And since then,
ومنذ تلك اللحظة
the automobile has allowed us the freedom
مكنتنا المركبات من التحرر
to choose where we live, where we work,
لنختار اين نعيش واين نعمل,
where we play
واين نلعب
and frankly when we just go out and want to move around.
وبأمانة عندما نخرج ونريد ان نتجول
We don't want to regress and lose that freedom.
لا نريد ان نتراجع ونخسر تلك الحرية المكتسبة.
We're on our way to solving --
نحن في طريقنا للحل--
and as I said earlier, I know we've got a long way to go --
وكما أسلفت, اعلم اننا امامنا طريق طويل لنسلكه--
the one big issue that we're all focused on that threatens it,
المشكلة الكبيرة التي نركز عليها جميعنا والتي تهددنا
and that's the environmental issue,
هي المشكلة البيئية,
but I believe we all must turn
ولكنني اعتقد ان جميعنا يجب ان نحول
all of our effort and all of our ingenuity and determination
جميع جهودنا وبراعتنا وتصميمنا
to help now solve this notion of global gridlock.
للمساعدة في حل مسألة الاختناق المروري العالمي
Because in doing so,
لأنه بعمل ذلك
we're going to preserve what we've really come to take for granted,
سوف نحافظ على ما حصلنا عليه و أصبح من المسلمات
which is the freedom to move
وهو حرية التنقل
and move very effortlessly around the world.
والتنقل بسلاسة حول العالم
And it frankly will enhance our quality of life
وذلك سوف يعزز مستوى المعيشة في حياتنا
if we fix this.
اذا اصلحنا هذا الامر
Because, if you can envision, as I do,
لانه اذا كنت تتصور,مثلي تمام,
a future of zero emissions
مستقبل بدون انبعاثات
and freedom to move around the country and around the world
وحرية في التنقل حول الدولة وحول العالم
like we take for granted today,
كما نفعل اليوم
that's worth the hard work today
فان ذلك يستحق العمل الشاق
to preserve that for tomorrow.
لحفظ ذلك للغد
I believe we're at our best
اؤمن اننا في افضل حالتنا
when we're confronted with big issues.
عندما نواجه المشاكل الكبيرة
This is a big one, and it won't wait.
هذه مشكلة كبيرة ولن تنتظر.
So let's get started now.
اذا لنبدأ الان
Thank you.
شكرا لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)